I bought over 500 houses in my life, but
I finally found the one that I wanted.
>> Want to take a walk with me through my
homestead in Costa Rica? It's one and a
half actas for about 2 and 1/2 acres
with a three-bedroom, two bath house,
over 100 fruit trees, six ponds with
lobsters and tilapia, a sawmill, a
trapiche, and numerous outings, some of
which we're about to convert to
cassitas, so you can come stay here one
day. It's hard to even want to see the
house, but let's go. The front porch is
vital to Costa Rican lifestyle. You'll
see Tico sitting on that porch every
single night just talking. Let's take a
look inside. First thing we have is a
full gift shop. I mean, a big ass gift
shop. Kind of ironic cuz I've never
tried to sell anything online. Look at
my solar website. Zero products for
sale. Full of some of the craziest
you've ever seen. Everything is teak.
From the roof decking to the roof
rafters to the columns right here to the
custom made doors and the hand cut trim.
Let's go this way. All of this is teak.
from the bead board to the window casing
to the lattice stripping to the wing
scoping. Why is tea so important? Well,
two reasons. One, it's impervious to
water. And two, insects don't like to
eat it. Termites are a huge problem down
here in Central America, and so they
live with tea. That way, they won't eat
that anyway. This is the dining
room in the kitchen, the heart of the
household. All Tiko families eat a
dinner here together every night. Food
is a social thing in Costa Rica. They
usually spend a lot of time cooking,
talking, and eating together every
evening, then outside on the porch in
the evening. Off the dining room, we
have a half bath. Tell me that ain't
Pablo Esco. Now, we're in the kitchen,
which has EBE cabinets.
EB will never rot, and it's so hard you
have to pre-drill it to get a screw in
it. You cannot drive a nail through it
at all. The tile countertops also double
as hot plates and cutting boards for
Tico families. Hey, let's go upstairs
first. Back to the dining room where
we're in this little portico. Absolutely
love the natural light. Tikico storage
closets beat the hell out of American
ones. Look at this. Once again, 100% te.
Then over here we have two bedrooms and
a shower. Let me explain Costa Rican
showers to you. Simple as hell. The
drains are all in the corner. They're
never in the middle. What they do is put
the base in and then just tilt the whole
thing and put regular floor tile on it.
You don't have to have mosaics or all
this crazy slooter You just have
to be okay with a hole in a different
spot. Water heaters here have exposed
electrical wires with wire nuts and
everything. 230 volts. Perfectly safe.
I've never died in any of them. Can you
shower in this? Would you be okay? If
not, stay your ass at home. Bedroom one.
Teddy bear. Tweedy bird. My levels.
Check the hand burnt tea curtain
palaces. Previous sellers are still
storing stuff in this bedroom. We're not
going in there out of respect. This is
the last and my favorite bedroom in the
house. Gift shop right below us.
Upstairs bedroom above. Could you wake
up to this every morning?
Now you know why I'm moving here. Solid
teak flooring and another full bathroom.
Once again, check the tico shower all in
one corner. Must have been leaking
there. They just smeared some concrete
there and it's going to push it back in
here. No problem. I absolutely love this
house, but I don't think OSHA would
agree. The view out the bathroom.
Now, let's go outside. This is the prep
room for everything homestead related.
First, we have a wood burning stove. Put
the wood in there. Light it up. This is
the prep sink where we clean all the
fish, lobsters, cut all the vegetables,
prep everything. When I sent traditional
homestead, I wasn't playing. A literal
grinding stone. This is the laundry sink
where the Tikos wash their clothes. Most
homesteads don't have a washer dryer.
We're fortunate enough to have one left
here by the sellers, but all the dirty
ass clothes are going to be prepped
here, and then they're squished down and
dried right here. Every morning I'll
wake up and go for a run first thing.
Then go down and hop in the Rio Celestee
across the street and come back and wash
my clothes in the sink as soon as I get
done. Use them every day, wash them
every day. Makes a lot of sense. This is
currently the commercial kitchen for the
cacao processing facility here. It
smells like straight chocolate breath.
This is all pure organic cacao. Not sure
what I'm going to do with this room, but
it's equipped with air conditioning.
Space age technology. Probably have it
for when the white folks come. Now for
my favorite part, the outside. This is
where we're going to build the eight
cassas. We'll come back to that. I got
about two dozen mature coconut trees
here. I drink two every day. My favorite
thing here. This lumber was milled right
here with the sawmill over there. This
is the sawmill.
>> This thing is old school as hell.
>> He's been using it for over 20 years.
Cannot argue with results. And behind
us, tons of trees. I don't want to cut
down any trees, but I also understand
all wood for all houses comes from a
trees. So, if I cut down one tree here
and plant back three more, it'll be
okay. Actually, renewable. These are all
the old cocoa pots from the harvest. I
wonder what the soil's like under there.
This is our area for cultivating.
Already loaded with mature plantains and
bananas. More over here, those in the
distance are papaya. See the flowers on
them? They're about to start bearing
fruit. This is a whole lot. But wait
till I show you the rest of the food
this place makes. This is where they dry
the cocoa beans. The seed you see here
is actually inside the fruit and you eat
away the meat around the seed and then
you dry this out. This is where your
chocolate comes from and your hot cocoa.
Pretty interesting. Bet you never knew
it. This is where we're going to put the
cassitas. My plan is to build eight of
them. Four on this side and four on the
other side with bathrooms in the middle.
Center drain line running down here
going out to the septic tank. La fafa.
Eight cassitas with tiny kitchens, beds,
baths, tables, all themed differently
with another part I love about Costa
Rica. Can't wait to do the native art
room estafa or the septic tank. There's
a human down inside that other one. You
can see his head. You can see those
Tikico's dug this by hand over a period
of 3 days.
>> I'm going to give him a tip. Up from
there we go to the first outdoor
kitchen. This is grand, isn't it?
Absolutely love this part. In here is an
outdoor kitchen.
Nice little sink. Here's the part I'm
turning into my first little tiny house
for me and Alex. This is going to be a
tiny house. Wall down the middle.
Bedroom on that side. Kitchen there.
Going to grow a tree right there where
the X is. We're going to put a door
right here and use this for our
bathroom. Change out this Costa Rican
urinal with a regular toilet. I am not
going to change the sink. This is
perfectly good to wash my hands. I'm so
proud of my fancy shower.
You give me a million dollars. I still
live dirty as Jesus would be
proud.
Build a wall here to close our bathroom
off from all the rest of the group
bathrooms right here. There's eight
toilets here. Four on each side.
A second outdoor kitchen currently
filled with frozen cacao. This is the
honored guest bedroom where esteemed
guests of honor get to spend the night.
Comes with its very own sitting rock.
Yoda approved.
Two more sinks here. Another laundry
sink. This out building is massive.
Group events, yoga retreats, UFC events,
whatever you want. Then there's another
one right here next to the pond. This is
what's in the pond. a freshwater
lobster. They're much like crawads, but
these things get huge. I have four ponds
of them here. This one, that one, number
three here. And number four right here.
There's cacao trees everywhere all along
the property. Probably two dozen in
total. Banana trees. Moduro.
This is the main tilapia pond where we
grow the big fish. It's kind of hard to
catch them out of there. So, we throw a
net in there and then transport them to
this pond right here. A lot easier to
catch them out of this pond with a cast
net than that one. This is our grove of
cacao trees. When the fruits are young,
they're purple and they turn yellow and
red the more ripe they get. Bananas.
>> I could pretend to tell you all the
names of these flowers, but I'd be
lying. The botany here is next level.
Look at the flowers on top of the
flower. This is all ornamental ginger.
So tall it forms a tunnel. Don't let the
red fool you. There's no hot water here.
You don't need it. It never gets cold. I
wish I could put the smell into a video
for you. Imagine cannabis without the
smell. It ain't
This is thee, a traditional Costa Rican
sugarce press. Strap two horses to it
like so. And as you push it around, it
grinds the gear and another person
catches it in the cup. Don't even need
solar to run it. Impressive. There's
going to be a door here that opens up to
our little deck that looks out over the
forest here in the back. Look at all the
papaya trees and all the massive old
grow forest. One day I'm going to build
a ropes course right off my deck
straight out into the trees.
[Music]
Did it. Time would fail me to show you
every plant, tree, flower on this
property, but look at the backdrop
behind me and listen. Nothing but water
and birds and bees. This is paradise. a
horicultural delight. It's literally
next to my house. Hope you enjoyed my
little slice of heaven here in Costa
Rica. Got a lot of work to do. Build an
entire Fels Tower renewable energy
center, a cassita tiny house. But I open
this place up so y'all can come see it
in person one day. I hope you get to see
my portovita.